#Section A
- Question: Give two characteristics of plantation farming
  Answer:
    - Production of one type of crop
    - Require large tract of land
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 1
  Marks: 1

- Question: Name two chemical processes of weathering
  Answer:
    - Carbonation
    - Oxidation
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 2
  Marks: 1

- Question: State two advantages of organic farming
  Answer:
    - Improves soil structure
    - Enhance soil water infiltration and retention
    - Provides food for soil microbes
    - Production of food free from chemical residues
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 3
  Marks: 1

- Question: Outline three effects of soil organisms which benefit plant growth
  Answer:
    - Improves aeration
    - Release soil nutrients when they decompose
    - Help in decomposition process
    - Promote nitrogen fixation
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 4
  Marks: 1

- Question: Give two ways in which organic mulch helps to conserve water in the soil
  Answer:
    - Reduce water loss through evaporation
    - Improve soil water infiltration and retention
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 5
  Marks: 1

- Question: Give two types of labour records
  Answer:
    - Labour utilization analysis
    - Muster roll
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 6
  Marks: 1

- Question: Outline four ways in which land consolidation helps to improve farm management
  Answer:
    - Proper supervision
    - Saves time and transportation cost
    - Facilitates soil conservation and farm mechanization
    - Legal ownership and title deed used to secure loans
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 7
  Marks: 2

- Question: State four importance of raising seedlings in a nursery bed
  Answer:
    - Excess sold for income
    - Facilitates planting of small seeds
    - Production of many seedlings in a small area
    - Management practices easily and timely carried out
    - Transplanting of only healthy and vigorously growing seedlings
    - Provide the best conditions for the growth of seedlings
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 8
  Marks: 2

- Question: Give four ways of controlling weeds in a field of maize
  Answer:
    - Uprooting
    - Cultivation/weeding with a jembe
    - Use of herbicides or chemical methods
    - Slashing weeds
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 9
  Marks: 2

- Question: State three reasons for top dressing pasture
  Answer:
    - Increase herbage yields
    - Improve nutritive value of the crop
    - Add soil nutrients
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 10
  Marks: 1.5

- Question: Give four reasons for training crops as a field practice
  Answer:
    - Plants grow in a designed direction and shape
    - Facilitates easy harvesting and spraying
    - Clean fruits are produced
    - Support plants
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 11
  Marks: 2

- Question: State three activities the farmer carries out on a store before storing grains
  Answer:
    - Cleaning the store/remove debris of previous crops
    - Dusting
    - Higher germination percentage
    - Pure/true to type
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 12
  Marks: 2

- Question: Give four desirable characteristics of certified seeds
  Answer:
    - High yielding
    - Pure/true to type
    - Clean/free seeds
    - High germination percentage
    - Healthy/free from pests and diseases
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 13
  Marks: 2

- Question: "Answer the following subquestions"
  Subquestions:
    - Subquestion: "(a) Outline two characteristics of nitrogenous fertilizers"
      Answer:
        - "Highly soluble"
        - "Easily leached"
        - "Scorching/burning effects"
        - "Highly volatile"
        - "Hygroscopic"
      Marks: 1
    - Subquestion: "(b) Give the forms in which the following elements are available to plants"
      Subquestions:
        - Subquestion: "(i) Phosphorous"
          Answer: "Phosphate ions (PO42-)"
          Marks: 0.5
        - Subquestion: "(ii) Potassium"
          Answer: "Potassium ions (K+)"
          Marks: 0.5
  QuestionNumber: 14
  Marks: 1
  Section: A

- Question: Give four factors that influence the choice of tools and equipment used in Primary cultivation
  Answer:
    - Condition of the land
    - Type of tilth required
    - Depth of cultivation
    - Availability/cost of the tool
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 15
  Marks: 2

- Question: State four factors that contribute to competitive ability of weeds
  Answer:
    - Produce large quantities of seeds
    - Seeds remain viable for long
    - Ability to propagate vegetatively
    - Seeds easily and successfully dispersed
    - Ability to grow in poor soil conditions
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 16
  Marks: 2

- Question: "Define the following terms as used in crop production"
  Subquestions:
    - Subquestion: "a) Trellishing"
      Answer: "- Supporting climbing plants e.g., passion fruits"
      Marks: 1
    - Subquestion: "b) Stooking"
      Answer: "- Cutting maize and arranging it vertically in groups in the field (OWTTE)"
      Marks: 1
  QuestionNumber: 17
  Marks: 2
  Section: A

- Question: Two advantages of strip grazing
  Answer:
    - Minimizes chances of animals getting bloat
    - Gives more productivity per unit area of land
    - The pasture is utilized more efficiently
    - Comparatively cheaper than constructing the paddocks
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 18
  Marks: 1

- Question: Four advantages of mixed pasture
  Answer:
    - Security against total loss due to pest and disease attack
    - High nutrient value and high yields
    - Lasts longer than pure stand pasture
    - Maximum use of nutrients
    - Better ground cover and better weed control
    - Economy on the use of nitrogen fertilizer
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 19
  Marks: 2

#Section B

- Question: "Study the diagram below and answer the questions that follow. The illustrations represent a method of crop propagation."
  Subquestions:
    - Subquestion: "a) Name the crop(s) propagated by the illustrations"
      Answer:
        - "A = Tea"
        - "B = Sugarcane"
      Marks: 1
    - Subquestion: "b) Give three factors that promote the rooting of illustration A"
      Answer:
        - "Oxygen supply"
        - "Rooting medium"
        - "Correct relative humidity"
        - "Suitable temperature"
        - "Suitable light intensity"
        - "Leaf area"
      Marks: 3
  QuestionNumber: 20
  Marks: 4
  Section: B

- Question: "The diagram below illustrates an experiment using garden soil. Study it carefully and answer the question that follows."
  Subquestions:
    - Subquestion: "a) What was the aim of the experiment?"
      Answer: "- To show that soil is made of different-sized particles"
      Marks: 1
    - Subquestion: "b) Name the parts labeled C and D."
      Answer: |
        - "C = Humus / organic matter"
        - "D = Gravel"
      Marks: 2
    - Subquestion: "c) Name the property of soil being investigated."
      Answer: "- Soil texture"
      Marks: 1
  QuestionNumber: 21
  Marks: 4
  Section: B

- Question: "The illustration below shows a type of soil erosion. Study it carefully and answer the questions that follow."
  Subquestions:
    - Subquestion: "a) Identify the type of erosion illustrated."
      Answer: "- Splash / Raindrop"
      Marks: 1
    - Subquestion: "b) Give two soil factors that influence the rate of soil erosion."
      Answer: 
        - "Soil depth / profile"
        - "Soil type"
      Marks: 2
    - Subquestion: "c) Name one agent of soil erosion."
      Answer: 
        - "Wind"
        - "Water"
        - "Human activities"
      Marks: 1
  QuestionNumber: 22
  Marks: 4
  Section: B

- Question: "The diagram below illustrates a method of irrigation carried out on the farm."
  Subquestions:
    - Subquestion: "(i) Identify the type of irrigation shown above."
      Answer: "Furrow irrigation"
      Marks: 1
    - Subquestion: "(ii) Name two advantages of the above method."
      Answer: 
        - "Reduce fungal diseases e.g., blight"
        - "Cheap to establish and maintain"
        - "Require little skills"
      Marks: 2
  QuestionNumber: 23
  Marks: 3
  Section: B

- Question: "The diagram below represents a method of manure preparation. Study it carefully and answer the questions that follow."
  Subquestions:
    - Subquestion: "a) Identify the type of manure being prepared."
      Answer: "Compost manure"
      Marks: 1
    - Subquestion: "b) Name the parts labeled E and F."
      Answer: 
        - "E = Dry leaves"
        - "F = Maize stalk"
      Marks: 1
    - Subquestion: "c) Give three disadvantages of manure."
      Answer: 
        - "Release nutrients slowly"
        - "Bulky"
        - "May be a source of weeds"
        - "Provide a breeding ground for pests"
        - "Difficult to quantify nutrients contained"
        - "Can only be used if fully decomposed"
      Marks: 3
  QuestionNumber: 24
  Marks: 12
  Section: B

#Section C
- Question: "Answer the following questions"
  Subquestions:
    - Subquestion: "(a) Give six precautions observed in pruning mature tea."
      Answer:
        - "Side branches should never be cut to encourage spread of tea bush."
        - "Avoid dish-shaped frame."
        - "Prune parallel with slope of ground, not horizontal."
        - "Cut branches across to minimize area of wound."
        - "Pruning knife should be sharp."
        - "Small branches and twigs on frame should be removed by hand."
        - "Leave branches to rot to release nutrients/act as mulch."
      Marks: 6
    - Subquestion: "(b) Describe the procedure followed when collecting a soil sample from the field for testing in the laboratory."
      Answer:
        - "Clear vegetation from sampling spot."
        - "Make a vertical act 15-25cm deep (crop land), 5cm pasture."
        - "Take a slice with spade/soil auger."
        - "Put the soil sample in a clean polythene bag."
        - "Repeat the 1-4 steps in 15-20 spots."
        - "Mix the sample thoroughly, dry, and crush."
        - "Take a sub-sample/composite sample to the laboratory for testing."
      Marks: 6
    - Subquestion: "(c) Outline four advantages of intercropping crops."
      Answer:
        - "Helps to control soil erosion."
        - "Good ground cover helps to smother weeds."
        - "Maximum utilization of the land."
        - "Adds soil nutrients in case legumes are intercropped."
      Marks: 4
    - Subquestion: "(d) Factors considered before selecting a farm enterprise."
      Answer:
        - "Land topography/drainage."
        - "Suitability of soil to the enterprise."
        - "Social-cultural factors."
        - "Taste/preference of the farmer."
        - "Availability of inputs."
        - "Size of the land available for the enterprise."
        - "The prevailing climate."
        - "Availability of market for the products."
        - "The period enterprise would take to mature."
        - "The current government policy."
        - "The common pests and diseases which may hinder the enterprise when implemented."
        - "Availability of capital."
        - "Land tenure system."
        - "Profit margin in relation to price fluctuation."
      Marks: 4
  QuestionNumber: 25
  Marks: 20
  Section: C

- Question: "Describe the production of tomatoes under the following subquestions"
  Subquestions:
    - Subquestion: "(i) Ecological requirements of tomato plants."
      Answer:
        - "Rainfall 760 – 1300mm p.a well distributed."
        - "Irrigation in dry areas/dry season."
        - "Attitude 0 – 2100 M a.s.l."
        - "Soil, deep, fertile, well-drained soils."
        - "Temperature 18 – 29°C/warm."
        - "Soil pH 6 – 6.5."
      Marks: 5
    - Subquestion: "(ii) Land preparations."
      Answer:
        - "Early land preparations before the onset of rains."
        - "Clear all vegetation."
        - "Remove tree stumps."
        - "Plough deep/primary cultivation."
        - "Harrow the land to medium tilth."
        - "Prepare planting holes 15cm deep."
        - "Spacing to be 0.9 x 0.6m/1.0m x 0.5m depending on varieties."
        - "Apply organicmanure/teaspoonfuls DSP."
      Marks: 4
    - Subquestion: "(iii) Transplanting."
      Answer:
        - "Done early in the morning or late in the evening."
        - "Water the nursery bed well."
        - "Use a garden trowel to lift the seedlings with a ball of soil around the root."
        - "Select only the healthy and vigorously growing seedlings."
        - "Place each seedling in the planting hole."
        - "Firm/compact the soil around the base of seedlings."
        - "Mulch the seedlings/shade if necessary."
        - "Water the seedlings."
      Marks: 7
    - Subquestion: "(iv) Disease control."
      Answer:
        - "Use appropriate chemicals to control disease."
        - "Ensure regular watering to control blossom end rot."
        - "Practice proper field hygiene/rogueing the infected plants."
        - "Plant resistant varieties."
      Marks: 4
  QuestionNumber: 26
  Marks: 20
  Section: C

- Question: "Answer the following questions"
  Subquestions:
    - Subquestion: "(a) Five factors that influence soil productivity."
      Answer:
        - "Good supply of crop nutrients."
        - "Well aerated."
        - "Good drainage."
        - "Abundance of useful soil microorganisms."
        - "Adequate water retention."
        - "Freedom from plant pests and diseases causing organisms."
        - "Free from noxious weeds e.g., witchweeds."
      Marks: 5
    - Subquestion: "(b) Qualities of a mother plant."
      Answer:
        - "High yielding."
        - "Resistant to pests/diseases."
        - "High-quality produce."
        - "High rooting ability."
        - "Early maturing."
        - "Should be compatible."
      Marks: 5
    - Subquestion: "(c) Two types of mulching materials."
      Answer:
        - "Organic mulches."
        - "Inorganic/synthetic mulches."
      Marks: 2
    - Subquestion: "(d) Agricultural practices that pollute water."
      Answer:
        - "Use of agro-chemicals in the farmlands."
        - "Cultivating along riverbanks, encouraging soil erosion, flooding, and siltation of streams, rivers, etc."
        - "Washing farm machines directly in water bodies."
        - "Overgrazing, leading to soil erosion and siltation of water sources."
      Marks: 4
    - Subquestion: "(e) Precautions when harvesting coffee."
      Answer:
        - "Overripe dark-colored cherries should not be picked."
        - "Underripe/green-colored cherries should not be picked."
        - "Sort out diseased berries before delivering to the factory to avoid pulping problems."
        - "Deliver cherries to the processing factory on the day of harvesting."
      Marks: 4
  QuestionNumber: 27
  Marks: 20
  Section: C
